Boker tov בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's daf דף daf is mem
gimmel מ"ג. mem gimmel. We pick up at the top of mem
gimmel מ"ג. mem gimmel. We're continuing the list of things that are
or are not forbidden for somebody that is assur אסור assur that
cannot get hana'ah הנאה hana'ah from somebody else. And we read, excuse
me, did I say mem gimmel מ"ג? mem gimmel? Mem bet מ"ב.
mem bet. Okay, top of mem bet מ"ב, mem bet, excuse me.
And okay, so daf דף daf is mem bet מ"ב. mem bet.
And the Mishnah משנה Mishnah says the following: Hamudar hana'ah mechavero lifnei
shevi'it המודר הנאה מחברו לפני שביעית. Hamudar hana'ah mechavero lifnei shevi'it. So
this Mishnah משנה Mishnah is actually going to be a little bit
more about shevi'it שביעית shevi'it than it is about somebody who cannot
get hana'ah הנאה. hana'ah. Somebody who is forsworn from getting benefit from
his friend before shevi'it שביעית, shevi'it, eino yored letoch sadehu אינו יורד
לתוך שדהו, eino yored letoch sadehu, you cannot go into the field,
ve'eino ochel min haneti'ot ואינו אוכל מן הנטיעות ve'eino ochel min haneti'ot
and you cannot eat even from the fruit that is from the
branches overhanging outside of the field. Okay, so basically indicating that if
you cannot get hana'ah הנאה, hana'ah, so hana'ah הנאה hana'ah includes not
only eating the fruit, but going into the field, right? We discussed
that before. You using somebody's yard, the right, like trespassing would be
if you're not allowed to use it, right? But the right to
walk in somebody's in somebody's house, in somebody's yard is considered a
form of hana'ah הנאה. hana'ah. So okay, so cannot get hana'ah הנאה
hana'ah means don't go into it and don't even pluck the fruit
from outside because you're then you're getting the fruit. Uveshevi'it ובשביעית, Uveshevi'it,
now there's two ways to read this Mishnah משנה. Mishnah. One is
once shevi'it שביעית shevi'it arrives, the neder נדר neder was from before
shemitah שמיטה shemitah and now shemitah שמיטה shemitah has arrived. We will
see that the Gemara גמרא Gemara will read this differently. If one
took the vow on
shevi'it שביעית, shevi'it, not that Reuven ראובן Reuven took a vow that
Shimon שמעון Shimon couldn't get benefit from him. So eino yored letoch
sadehu אינו יורד לתוך שדהו, eino yored letoch sadehu, he cannot enter
into Reuven's ראובן Reuven field, aval ochel hu min haneti'ot hannotot אבל
אוכל הוא מן הנטיעות הנוטות aval ochel hu min haneti'ot hannotot or
min haneti'ot מן הנטיעות, min haneti'ot, but he can eat from the
fruit of the branches that are overhanging outside the field. Why could
he eat from Reuven's ראובן Reuven fruit if Reuven ראובן Reuven took
the vow on shevi'it שביעית? shevi'it? He can't on
shevi'it שביעית, shevi'it, right. It's not Reuven's ראובן Reuven fruit to make
forbidden. Okay, but what's interesting is it still is Reuven's ראובן Reuven
field. All right, now it's his property. You don't lose ownership of
the property. Okay. Now the interesting thing the Gemara גמרא Gemara is
going to say is but don't you lose the right to prevent
people from walking into your
property because aren't the poor allowed free access in your property in
order to eat the fruit? And therefore how were you allowed to
make forbidden, right, if you couldn't make the fruit forbidden, how could
you make access into your property forbidden? I mean, if you could,
that would be a good way that everybody could stop people from
going into their yard on shevi'it שביעית, shevi'it, just make the access
to their property forbidden. Okay, but that seems that that actually does
work. Okay, so but so the simple explanation is the fruit isn't
yours, you can't make that forbidden, but the property and access to
the property is and that remains forbidden. Now again, one way of
reading the Mishnah
משנה Mishnah is is that the vow the vow was taken before
shevi'it שביעית shevi'it and everything was forbidden, would then the fruit become
permissible once shevi'it שביעית shevi'it has arrived? Okay, so that's going to
be what the Gemara גמרא Gemara will discuss. So anyway, let's take
a look. Nadar mimenu ma'achal lifnei shevi'it נדר ממנו מאכל לפני שביעית.
Nadar mimenu ma'achal lifnei shevi'it. Let's say the only neder נדר neder
was you cannot get any food benefit. So if that was from
before shevi'it שביעית, shevi'it, yored letoch sadehu ve'eino ochel min haperot יורד
לתוך שדהו ואינו אוכל מן הפירות. yored letoch sadehu ve'eino ochel min
haperot. You can have access to the field, that's not food, but
you still but you cannot eat the fruit. Uvashevi'it ובשביעית Uvashevi'it and
on shevi'it שביעית, shevi'it, yored ve'ochel יורד ואוכל, yored ve'ochel, you both
have access to the field, that's not food, and you also can
eat the fruit because that the person cannot make forbidden, it's not
his. Okay, so pretty straightforward Mishnah משנה, Mishnah, the basic question we
have is this issue about access to the yard, why you're allowed
to make that forbidden on shevi'it שביעית shevi'it if the aniyim עניים
aniyim are allowed to have access into your yard. But the Gemara
גמרא Gemara is going to sort of focus on the first question,
which is which boils down to: do you read the Mishnah משנה
Mishnah when it says on shevi'it שביעית shevi'it that once shevi'it שביעית
shevi'it arrives, the neder נדר neder stops being effective vis-à-vis the fruit?
Or do you read it if you took the neder נדר neder
on shevi'it שביעית shevi'it it's not effective vis-à-vis the fruit? So let's
take a look. Rav uShmuel de'amri tarvaihu רב ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו, Rav
uShmuel de'amri tarvaihu, Rav רב Rav and Shmuel שמואל Shmuel both say:
if somebody said "nechasim elu alecha" נכסים אלו עליך, nechasim elu alecha,
"these are this property is forbidden to you" lifnei shevi'it לפני שביעית,
lifnei shevi'it, if he said it before shevi'it שביעית, shevi'it, eino yored
letoch sadehu ve'eino ochel min haneti'ot אינו יורד לתוך שדהו ואינו אוכל
מן הנטיעות, eino yored letoch sadehu ve'eino ochel min haneti'ot, you cannot
go into the field, that's the property is forbidden in terms of
access to the yard, and you cannot even eat from the fruit
that's overhanging. Af al pi shehigi'a shevi'it אף על פי שהגיעה שביעית,
Af al pi shehigi'a shevi'it, even once shevi'it שביעית shevi'it arrives, once
the neder's נדר neder in effect, it doesn't stop. Even though the
fruit now becomes ownerless, right, if I go ahead and I say
to somebody "my sefer ספר sefer here is forbidden to you" or
not let's say I don't say "mine," that's going to be a
little bit more complicated, let's say I say "this sefer ספר sefer
is forbidden to you" and currently I own it, and then I
sell it to somebody, it remains forbidden to Shimon שמעון. Shimon. I
made it forbidden and even once I stop owning it, right, the
same way I it doesn't change sort of that status, at least
that's the assumption that we have. So they said "this fruit is
forbidden," they said "this fruit is forbidden." So now yes, it became
shevi'it שביעית, shevi'it, they don't own the fruit anymore, but its forbidden
status. status remains because when he made the נדר, neder, it was
his to make that נדר. neder. Now presumably new fruit that would
grow, that would be permissible because that person wouldn't own it. So
even though I said all of my fruit is forbidden, you know,
from here and in the future on שמעון, Shimon, I still couldn't
make the fruit that grew on שמיטה Shmita forbidden. That would not
have been mine to begin with. But this fruit that is currently
forbidden remains forbidden even once it becomes ownerless. So when the משנה
Mishnah says that on שמיטה Shmita it's permissible, it doesn't mean that
the vow made before... the fruit that was forbidden before שמיטה Shmita
becomes permissible on שמיטה. Shmita. It means if you took the vow
on שמיטה, Shmita, then the fruit is permissible. But if you took
it before, it remains forbidden. Yes.
So the original owner of the book can make a conditional sale
about who the new owner...
what he... the sale wouldn't be conditional. Like people should be aware...
I might want to tell you if I'm selling to you "Be
aware by the way that this book is אסור assur on שמעון."
Shimon. So, you know, you might want to avoid selling it to
שמעון Shimon because then שמעון Shimon will transgress or whatever. But it's
not conditional. I mean, you can go ahead and sell it to
him and then, you know, it's just that...
But he can't sell it to שמעון. Shimon.
Well, or שמעון Shimon more specifically can't buy it, you know...
But you know what I'm saying? It's like... well, that's a good
question. It might be לפני עור lifnei iveir by selling it to
שמעון. Shimon. Yeah, I mean, that might be true. I mean, interesting
question. Let's say שמעון Shimon buys it but doesn't
actually... how have we dealt with that? Use it, right, because we
dealt with whether an actual sale is considered הנאה, hana'ah, but that's
when I can't benefit from a person. I can't benefit from a
person's property and I pay for it, so have I yet benefited
from the property?
I'm not sure. It's an interesting question. Interestingly, we haven't dealt with
that. We've dealt with that a sale is considered to be a
benefit of both sides, right, but that's when the הנאה hana'ah is
from the person. But it's הנאה hana'ah from the property. Again, if
you're paying for the property, I'm not sure.
What about the lien?
What do you
mean in terms of this... you're selling... I mean not regarding the
sale to שמעון, Shimon, but in general that the ownership that the
person... that the buyer takes in it includes this little...
right, right, right, this thing that doesn't go away. Right, exactly. Okay,
so... okay... anyway they say that the משנה Mishnah means if you
took the vow on שמיטה, Shmita, it's not binding by the fruit,
but if you took the vow before שמיטה, Shmita, it remains
binding. Okay. רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש דאמרי תרווייהו, Rebbi Yochanan v'Reish Lakish
d'amri tarvaihu, רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש Rebbi Yochanan v'Reish Lakish both say...
yes... oh, I'm sorry... רב אפרים... Reb Ephraim...
everybody in this town can't... how could you just אסור assur this
stuff through שמיטה... Shmita... it was just...
No, you... oh
you mean...
Nobody in this town is allowed, you know, to buy stuff.
You mean and that actually's a good way of people keeping people
off of your fruit on שמיטה. Shmita. I mean, it's a good
point. It won't keep them off of the stuff that grows... well,
look, look at it this way. If I wanted to, I could
harvest all the fruit from before שמיטה Shmita and keep it away
from people. I can't אסור assur the new stuff. I can only
אסור assur the old stuff. But I guess you're right, so it's
not a way like I'm tricking שמיטה, Shmita, because the same stuff
that I'm forbidding is stuff that I could have harvested and locked
up and kept away before שמיטה. Shmita. But I guess the difference
is, here's an interesting question, if it continues to grow, right, so
that is what I would gain. Like if I've got fruit on
the tree and it's not ready to be harvested yet, right, and
it's right before שמיטה Shmita and I say this is אסור assur
to everybody, right, and it remains אסור, assur, so then and then
maybe after שמיטה Shmita passes then I go get a היתר heter
on my נדר neder or something. I don't know what I would
do. Or maybe I just say it's אסור assur for the next
year, right,
and... so I really don't have the ability to אסור assur the
continued growth of the fruit, but how is somebody going to sort
of cut away the new stuff, right? So it's an interesting point.
You can use it as a device to keep people off the
stuff. It's true. It's true. I mean, you can only אסור assur
the stuff that exists right now, but if you've got an apple
and it continues to grow, right, how is somebody else going to
get access to the part of the apple that they're allowed to
use, right? Yeah, it's a very good point. And... yeah, I don't
know, I hadn't thought about that. I mean, it's similar to my
question before, which is if you can just make people... forbid people
from going through your yard, it's a good effective way of getting
people off the ground. But you're right, you're right, I mean this
also would about the continued growth. But the stuff that already exists
that's not going to continue to grow, that's not... I don't care,
so what, you could harvest it also before שמיטה Shmita and prevent
people. All right. ואם בשביעית נדר, v'im b'shvi'is nadar, if the vow
was on שמיטה, Shmita, אין יורד לתוך שדהו אבל אוכל מן הנוטות,
ein yored l'toch sadeh aval ochel min hanotos, then you can't go
into the yard, but you can eat from the fruit. The vow
on שמיטה Shmita won't apply because it's not your fruit. But from
before שמיטה Shmita it will continue to apply on
שמיטה. Shmita. רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש דאמרי תרווייהו, Rebbi Yochanan v'Reish Lakish
d'amri tarvaihu, רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש Rebbi Yochanan v'Reish Lakish both say:
נכסיי עליך, nechasai alecha, if somebody says "My property is forbidden to
you" לפני שביעית, lifnei shvi'is, before שמיטה, Shmita, אין יורד לתוך שדהו
ואינו אוכל מן הנוטות, ein yored l'toch sadeh v'eino ochel min hanotos,
obviously can't go to the yard and can't eat the fruit.
But הגיע שביעית... hegia shvi'is... but even הגיע שביעית, higiah Shvi'is, I'm
sorry, but, I was right the first time, but הגיע שביעית, higiah
Shvi'is, אינו יורד לתוך שדיהו, eino yored l'tokh sadeihu, you still can't
go into the yard, אבל אוכל הוא את הנטות, aval okhel hu
es hantot, but you can eat the stuff that is overhanging outside
of the yard because even if you made it אסור assur before
שמיטה, Shmita, when שמיטה Shmita comes about, it stops being אסור. assur.
Okay? So they say that yes, you made this fruit אסור assur
before שמיטה, Shmita, but now that it's שמיטה Shmita and you don't
own this fruit anymore, presumably your איסור, issur, your, you know, your
the status you instilled in it is no longer effective cause it's
no longer yours that your נדר neder should have the power to
make it forbidden. All right? So and presumably they read the משנה
Mishna that not if you made the vow on שמיטה, Shmita, but
once שמיטה Shmita comes about, the food becomes permissible. Okay? So that
seems to be a really interesting debate. I can go ahead and
say, right, Jonathan's car is forbidden to me, or that car out
there parked out in the front yard is forbidden to me, and
then it'll remain forbidden whoever he sells it to, because I can
make anybody's property forbidden to me. So whether it's Jonathan's, or Doe's,
or Joe's, or David, or whoever's it is, right, I said the
car's forbidden, it remains forbidden whoever gets ownership. But if I say
my car is forbidden on Jonathan, I only have the power to
make it forbidden because it's mine, right? So now it becomes the
question: once I stop owning it and somebody else owns it, maybe
my status
doesn't persist once it's out of my control cause my ability to
make it forbidden on somebody else was a virtue of my control.
So maybe that state can't continue after I no longer have the
control over that object, after I no longer own that object. So
that's a way of explaining it, which is the most interesting way.
It's not a question of what your כוונה kavana is, it's a
question of your actual power to make a נדר, neder, your power
to make your thing forbidden on others, only extends as far as
your ownership of that object extends. So they're reading the משנה, Mishna,
the fruit is forbidden before שמיטה Shmita arrives, but once שמיטה Shmita
arrives, it's no longer yours and therefore becomes permissible. Let's see what
the גמרא Gemara does with that. That would be the most interesting
way to read what רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש Rebbe Yochanan v'Reish Lakish
just said.
Okay,
so why isn't the book also then?
After he no longer
owns the book.
Yeah, according to that logic, if I say my book is forbidden
to Jonathan and then I sold it to you, it's now permissible
because my ability to make this forbidden to somebody else was only
by virtue of my
power.
But you said if he says "this book"...
Well, right now I'm not making a difference. The גמרא's Gemara going
to make a difference between "mine" and "this" and all of that.
Okay, but without making any of that difference, we could conceptually say
that whether I said "my book," "this book," whatever I said, even
if I said "this book is forbidden on Jonathan for infinity, for
forever," nevertheless, maybe I don't have the power to make it forbidden
once it stops being mine. Okay, so that's the interesting conceptual way
of explaining it. It's not a function of what I intended or
what I said, it's the limits of my power. All right? And
therefore the fruit would become permissible once it was no longer mine.
Now the גמרא's Gemara going to not go that sort of qualify
it, but that's at least the most interesting way of reading רבי
יוחנן וריש לקיש. Rebbe Yochanan v'Reish Lakish. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this: לימא ובהא קמיפלגי, Leima u'v'ha kamifligi, let's say this is
what the debate is. ד רב ושמואל סברי, D'Rav u'Shmuel savri, אדם
אוסר דבר שברשותו adam oser davar she'birshuso אפילו לכשיצא מרשותו. afilu l'khesheyeitzei
mershuso. Right,
here the גמרא Gemara says exactly that. Let's say Rav and Shmuel
say that a person can make something that's in his control, ownership,
forbidden, and it will persist with its status even after it leaves
his control. ורבי יוחנן וריש לקיש סברי, V'Rebbe Yochanan v'Reish Lakish savri,
but Rebbe Yochanan and Reish Lakish hold, אין אדם אוסר
דבר שברשותו לכשיצא מרשותו. ein adam oser davar she'birshuso l'khesheyeitzei mershuso. They
do not make, you do not have the power to make it
forbidden once it leaves your control. Okay? So your power to make
it forbidden on somebody else is a function of your ownership, it
does not extend beyond your actual ownership of that object. That's a
great debate. So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, it can't be
that fundamental of a debate. ותסברא, V'sisbara, does this really make sense?
מי איכא למאן דאמר אין אדם אוסר דבר שברשותו לכשיצא מרשותו? Mi
ika l'man de'amar ein adam oser davar she'birshuso l'khesheyeitzei mershuso? Who says
you cannot make something forbidden even after it leaves your control? אם
כן, Im kein, first of all, if that were true, נפלוג בנכסים
אלו וכל שכן בנכסיי. niflog bi'nekhasim eilu v'kol shekein bi'nekhasi.
So first it points the thing that David said, which is, if
it's a fundamental question, then they should have said their position that
it becomes permissible even if you just said "this property is forbidden
to Shimon."
But if you take a look at the language that רבי יוחנן
וריש לקיש Rebbe Yochanan v'Reish Lakish used, they say, "my property this,"
or just "my property," excuse me, נכסיי עליך, nekhasai alekha,
"my property is forbidden to you." So why's it different if you
say "this property" or "my property"? Why? Why do you think it
makes a difference? Why is "my property" different than "this property"?
Because
one is
possession. Because if I say "my car is forbidden to
you," fine, then
it means as long as So it doesn't sound like it's so
fundamental. It sounds like it's specifically because you said the possessive mine
that your נדר neder is limited to your ownership over it. That's
number one. So נפשוט בנכסים אלו, nifshot benichasim elu, these properties, these
you know objects, וכל שכן בנכסי vechol sheken benichasai certainly if even
there your נדר neder won't persist, certainly when you say my property.
But two, number one, so it sounds like it's only because you
said my. התנן hatnan and I'll bring you evidence that there's a
משנה mishna that of course you can make something forbidden as it
continues to be you know even after it leaves your control. התנן
דאדם אוסר דבר שברשותו
לכשיצא מרשותו. hatnan de'adam oser davar shebirshuto lichsheyetzei meirshuto. We taught in
the משנה: mishna: אומר לבנו, omer livno, somebody says to a son,
קונם שאתה נהנה לי, konam she'atah neheneh li, קרבן, korban, like אסור,
assur, you know by נדר neder is all of my property that
you cannot get benefit from me. מת, met, if he dies, ירשנו,
yirshenu, he actually can inherit him and benefit from the property. Why?
Because from me you're getting benefit from me. So
interestingly, when a person inherits, it seems that the inheritance happens like
after the death occurs. So if that inheritance happens or at the
moment of death, after the death, whatever, but you're not getting benefit
from that person, it was never his property. It went from being
his property to being like your property, but it was your property
when the guy was already dead. So right? It's not like a
sale. If he would have given something to his son, then he
is getting something from ראובן. Reuven. But interestingly, the way inheritance looks
like is he's not getting something from ראובן. Reuven. So it's supposed
to look like ראובן Reuven is dead and now he's getting ראובן's
Reuven property, what used to be ראובן's Reuven property, but he's not
getting it from ראובן, Reuven, ראובן's Reuven already dead. So therefore he's
actually, it actually is permissible to get benefit. בחייו ובמותו. bechayav uvemoto.
But if ראובן Reuven said to his son: you cannot get benefit
from this property in my life or after my death, then מת
לא ירשנו, met lo yirshenu, he does not inherit.
Now actually this gets interesting because the רן Ran says, this goes
back to the question David we were having about can you buy
the object if you're not going to benefit from it. If you
take a look at the רן, Ran, the רן Ran says
where's the רן? Ran? Maybe it's on the
yeah the very last רן Ran of עמוד א. amud alef. מת
לא ירשנו לאו דוקא לא ירשנו דנכסי ודאי דידיה הוו וכמו שנתבאר
בפרקין דלקמן. met lo yirshenu lav davka lo yirshenu denichasai vadai didei
havu uchemo shenitba'er bepirkin deleikaman. He
says the guy would obviously inherit the property, he would own it,
but what he means is you're not allowed to, the person can't
get benefit from the property. So that would be actually interesting. His
actual ownership and the fact that it would be like listed, you
know, in his possession is not considered benefit itself, or maybe it
is but there's no way the הנאה hana'ah can prevent the automatic
sort of change of ownership from happening. Like the נדר neder doesn't
stop that, that happens in חושן משפט, choshen mishpat, that happens automatically,
right?
So therefore it's not that the person doesn't own it, it's just
he owns it now but he's not allowed to benefit. He can't
sell it, he can't use it, he can't benefit from it, but
he owns it. Okay, so that's interesting, right? Can you actually get
the objects into your possession without actually getting any benefit from it?
Does it mean he could either give it to somebody
or pay oh well that's interesting. Well, maybe if he dies, right,
he probably couldn't give it, that probably would be considered benefit of
טובת הנאה, tovat hana'ah, the person would be grateful. But it's an
interesting question of could he bequeath it, right? Because then he actually,
whatever he might be getting from it he's not getting after it.
Unless of course the kids are extra nice to him because they
know they're standing to inherit, and then it's an interesting question. Anyway,
but for us what's important is on the one hand this is
fascinating that when a person gets the inheritance he's getting it after
the person is dead so he's not getting it from the person
and therefore if he meant from me you can't get benefit it
would not be a problem. But if he basically said you can't
get benefit from this property even after I'm dead then that prohibition
remains. So you see that you can make your stuff forbidden on
somebody even after you stop owning it. So you see that clearly
is something that's agreed upon. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, and
again conceptually that's interesting because you certainly could have conceptually understood why
you would not have the power to do that. So the גמרא
Gemara says: so you're right. שאני הכא דקאמר ליה בחייו ובמותו. shani
hacha deka'amar lei bechayav uvemoto. Okay, but there maybe he said it
explicitly. So maybe you do have that power but you have to
be explicit about it that you're going to make something forbidden even
after you stop owning it. So if I just said my car,
if I just said the car is forbidden to you. this car,
this car is forbidden to you, without explicating, it would be assumed
to mean as long as I own it. Because since fundamentally that's
where my power derives from is the fact that, you know, it's
mine and I control it, we'll interpret my statement to be as
long as I own it, but אי הכי נמי ei hachi nami
if you explicitly said even after I sell it, then that would
be effective. So why to interpret the statement implicitly that way, I
sort of said because I still want to hold onto this idea
because fundamentally your your ability to make it forbidden is rooted in
your ownership and in your power of it. The ר"ן Ran also
just to get... the ר"ן Ran makes it more psychological. Like if
I say I don't want to get benefit from that car, right,
that Jonathan owns. So it's really about me and the car. It's
not about Jonathan. I just don't want to get benefit from Jonathan
and from that car, so that obviously will continue to be even
after he sells it. But if I say to somebody, right, you
know, this car is forbidden to you, primarily it's about my relationship
with that person. So why should I really care so much if
I don't own the car anymore? So the ר"ן Ran wants to
make it psychological, that the reason we would interpret your statement fundamentally
to be as long as you own it is because you probably
care more about the נדר neder because of, you know, because it's
about you and that other person. You probably don't care as much
once you stop owning it. I would like to still go back
to the original idea, that since your power to make it forbidden
is rooted in your ownership, then we will be inclined to interpret
your נדר neder limited to the time of your actual ownership. But
if you're explicit about it, yes, you can make it persist even
beyond that. Jonathan, you had a question.
What about the laws of ירושה yerushah דאורייתא? d'Oraisa? Yes. So how
do you do that?
Well, you didn't stop the person from inheriting it, you just made
it אסור בנדר. assur be'neder. The laws of, right? I
mean, לא יירשנו? lo yirshenu? דאורייתא. d'Oraisa. The ר"ן Ran says it
doesn't mean לא יירשנו. lo yirshenu. It means you can't get benefit.
The guy inherits it, but he can't get benefit from it.
Is that not an עבירה aveirah situation?
Well, it might be. But all right. So... all right. So now
the... okay, anyway, so but what you see is, so the גמרא
Gemara says it's possible to still hold that without being explicit about
it, the נדר neder doesn't persist. So, but it's not as fundamental
of a debate as we thought. Okay, so yes it's true that
that they have to concede that something will can remain forbidden after
the person stops owning it. But still maybe they would say in
the standard case we wouldn't say that. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara
says if that's true though, they still want to say in a
standard case it would be limited to the time he owned it,
מכל מקום michol makom says the גמרא, Gemara, קשיא, kashya, it's we
still have the difficulty that we had. Okay, meaning what's the difficulty
that we had? That if they really wanted to say that fundamentally
it was limited to the time he owned it, they wouldn't... רב
Rav and שמואל Shmuel would not have given their example if the
guy said my property. If you want to say that a basic
נדר neder is interpreted to be limited to the time when you
own it, then just say if the person had said this property
rather than my. By them giving their example when the person said
my property, it's permitted when שמיטה Shmita comes about, seems to be
that they're saying only because you used the possessive my does it
stop being applicable after you stop owning it. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says, you know what, that's a good point. The fact that
they said my indicates that they're limiting their statement to because you
used that possessive. אלא בנכסים אלו, Ela benechasim elu, if you say
generically this property, כולי עלמא לא פליגי, kulei alma lo peligi,
then nobody debates that then it persists, you know, even after you
stop owning it.
כי פליגי בנכסיי, Ki peligi benechasai, my property. רב Rav and שמואל
Shmuel סברי לא שנא נכסים אלו ולא שנא נכסיי, savri lo shana
nechasim elu velo shana nechasai, it doesn't matter whether you say this
property or my property. אדם אוסר, Adam oser, we will say that
the status will continue afterwards. So if a person made the property
forbidden before שמיטה, Shmita, whether he said my property or this property,
it remains forbidden even when שמיטה Shmita arrives. That's what they would
say. And they would explain the משנה Mishna that it was when
you made the נדר neder on שמיטה, Shmita, that would be different.
But if you made the נדר neder before שמיטה, Shmita, it would
remain when שמיטה Shmita arrived, whether you said this property or my
property. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Resh Lakish and they
hold, look, we agree that if you said this property, then it
persists. Yes, if you make a נדר neder when you own something,
it will persist when you stop owning it. But if you said
נכסיי, nechasai, and he tries to get... it's נכסיי nechasai not נכסים,
nechasim, if you said my... I'm sorry, excuse me, no I was
right the first time, נכסים אלו, nechasim elu, this property, or נכסיי
אלו, nechasai elu, you know, this property, נכסים אלו, nechasim elu, then
אדם אוסר Adam oser and yes, it will persist, I agree, in
principle it can persist and if you say this property, it will
persist. But if you say נכסיי, nechasai, my property, אין אדם אוסר,
ein Adam oser, then it doesn't persist. Okay, so it's a simple
debate. Everybody agrees in principle it can persist if you say this
property, but when you say my property, then do we interpret it
to mean only as long as I own it? And that's the
debate, if somebody said my property before or שמיטה Shmita will the
stuff become permissible once שמיטה Shmita arrives? All right, so that's the
question. So the גמרא Gemara says, what it says like this. ומי
איכא למאן דאמר לא שנא נכסים אלו ולא שנא נכסיי? U'mi ika
le'man de'amar lo shna nechasim elu velo shna nechasai? Wait
a minute says the גמרא, Gemara, you've explained Rabbi Yochanan and Resh
Lakish. They clearly are saying because you say 'my property', it doesn't
persist after you stop owning it. But is it really true that
Rav and Shmuel would say that even if you use the possessive,
that it continues even after your ownership ceases? Is that... does anybody
say that? ומי איכא למאן דאמר לא שנא נכסים אלו ולא שנא
נכסיי, U'mi ika le'man de'amar lo shna nechasim elu velo shna nechasai,
is there anyone who says it doesn't matter whether you say 'this
property' or 'my property' that it remains forbidden even after you stop
owning it? דתנן במתניתין, De'tenan be'matnitin, אומר לחברו, Omer le'chavero,
קונם לתוך ביתך שאני נכנס, Konam letoch beitecha she'ani nichnas,
Korban your house is forbidden to me that I can't enter into
it, okay the key being he said your house. Okay. שדך שאני
לוקח, Sadecha she'ani loke'ach, your field that I won't purchase it. מת,
Meit, if the owner of the house or the field died, או
שמכרו לאחר, O she'macharo le'acher, or he sold the field or the
house to somebody else, מותר, Mutar, then it's permissible, because he said
'your' house I won't go into. If he said לבית זה שאני
נכנס, Le'bayit zeh she'ani nichnas, I won't go into this house, שדה
זו שאני לוקח, Sadeh zo she'ani loke'ach, I won't purchase this field,
then מת או שמכרו לאחר אסור, Meit o she'macharo le'acher assur, then
if he sells it, it's forbidden. So it's very clear that the
possessive means as long as this person is owning it. And if
that's true when it's about somebody else's field, right? Then... and where
clearly I could make this, you know, clearly it doesn't really matter
who's owning it, I'm making it forbidden to me, but the possessive
means as long as you own it. So when I make my
field אסור Assur and I use the word 'my field' and again
there my whole power to make it forbidden is rooted in my
ownership and I use the possessive, then presumably everybody would agree, right,
that it would stop being forbidden once I sold it. So the
גמרא Gemara said,
אלא, Ela, גמרא Gemara says, you know what, you're right. You've proven
that when you say a generic 'this', everybody agrees that it's forbidden
even after you stop owning it. And if you say the possessive
'mine', everybody agrees it's permissible after you stop owning it. So then
actually nobody's debating. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, so כי אמר
רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש בנכסיי, Ki amar Rabbi Yochanan ve'Reish Lakish be'nechasai,
אלא Ela you're right, when Rabbi Yochanan and
Resh Lakish said it becomes permissible after you stop owning it is
when it says 'my property'. Then it's permissible when שמיטה Shmita when
I stop owning it. ורב ושמואל בנכסים אלו, Ve'Rav u'Shmuel be'nechasim elu,
and when do Rav and Shmuel say it remains forbidden even after
you stop owning it? It's when you say 'these' you know 'this
property'. ולא פליגי, Velo pligi, and they're actually not debating and if
you go back and look, Rav and Shmuel said when you say
נכסים אלו Nechasim elu it's forbidden even when שמיטה Shmita arrives, and
Rabbi Yochanan and Resh Lakish say when you say נכסיי Nechasai it's
permissible when שמיטה Shmita arrives, and they're both talking about two scenarios
of the same case. They're not disagreeing. נכסים אלו Nechasim elu remains
forbidden, נכסיי Nechasai becomes permissible. And therefore how do you read the
משנה? Mishnah? Right? So therefore, you know,
the משנה Mishnah isn't clear whether you say נכסיי Nechasai or נכסים.
Nechasim. Right, they might be giving two interpretations. I don't think it
says explicitly in the משנה. Mishnah. Right? So they might be giving
two interpretations of the משנה. Mishnah. If you read the משנה Mishnah
as the guy said 'this property is forbidden to you', right? Then
the משנה Mishnah would be saying that not that when שמיטה Shmita
comes it becomes permissible, but if you made the נדר Neder on
שמיטה Shmita it's permissible, but when שמיטה Shmita comes it won't change
the status because you said 'this property'. Whereas the other person might
say, Rabbi Yochanan and Resh Lakish might say, no, here's the way
you read the משנה. Mishnah. The guy said 'my property is forbidden'.
Okay, so therefore before שמיטה Shmita it's forbidden and once שמיטה Shmita
comes about then it becomes permissible. So that could be giving two
ways of reading the משנה Mishnah based on whether you said 'my
property' or 'this property'. But everybody really agrees. So it was a
great הוה אמינא Hava amina that your ability to make something forbidden
is rooted in your ownership and therefore it doesn't persist after you
stop owning, but at the end of the day we say that's
not true and we say that actually the key is whether you
said generic or whether you said the possessive. Now, what let's say
you said both? Okay, so the רן Ran here at the bottom
quotes an interesting ירושלמי Yerushalmi and he says like this. He says,
one minute...
so the רן Ran says,
it's like one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, ten lines from
the bottom, like right on top of the word, you see where
it says הרי Harei in sort of a little bold? So a
little on the line on top of that, a little bit before,
it says like this. It says: הוא הדין בנכסי אלו דאדם אוסר.
Hu hadin be'nechasai elu de'adam oser.
Now let's say you said 'my property this'. You said both the
word 'this' and 'my'. Okay, so you said 'my property this' is
forbidden to you. So does it emphasize the 'this'? the object regardless
of ownership or does it emphasize the mine and does it remain
forbidden even after I stop owning it? Okay. שהולכין אחר לשון אחרון.
She-holchin achar lashon acharon.
He says you go by the last word when he says these
or this דאמר אלו de-amar eilu ובהכי איתא בירושלמי
ביתך זה. uv-hachi ita Beyerushalmi beitecha zeh. Your house, this one, I
won't go into it. So what happens when you stop owning it?
Do you say you said your house or do I say your
house this, this house? So is it this house I won't go
into or is it your house I won't go into? So משום
מה תפסתה? mishum mah tafasta? משום ביתך? mishum beitecha?
How do you emphasize what he said? The your house or משום
זה mishum zeh or the this house? ומסקנת הירושלמי Umaskanat Ha-Yerushalmi concludes
משום זה, mishum zeh, you go by the last phrase, the this.
Okay, so that's interesting. If the possessive means as long as you
own it or as long as I own it, let's say you
both say a possessive and a what's the word and a this
which emphasizes the object itself, not the ownership of the object. So
which one do you use to interpret it? Okay, but anyway, but
if you just say the mine or you just say this, then
mine is as long as I own it and this is forever.
Okay, so that's the mishnah. Okay, now ובשביעית, U-vishvi'it, so what
again, if the neder was made on שמיטה shemitah you can't make
the food forbidden or even if it was made before, if you
say my food, my food, it stops being forbidden when שמיטה shemitah
arrives. But what you cannot but what
your neder clearly even on שמיטה shemitah can prevent the guy from
going into your field. Now why is that? So בשביעית אין יכול
לתפוס שדהו. Bishvi'it ein yachol litpos sadehu. מאי שנא דאוכל מן הנוטות?
Mai shna de-ochel min ha-notot?
Why is the neder as made on שמיטה shemitah can you eat
from the overhanging fruit? דפירי דהפקירא אינון, Depirei de-hefkeira inun, it's ownerless
fruit. You can't, it's not yours to make forbidden. So ארעא נמי
אפקרא, Ar'a nami apkarah, so the fruit is also forbidden, I mean
not forbidden, excuse me, ownerless, the fruit, that's it. Try that again.
The land also is ownerless. Now it doesn't literally mean ownerless, but
it means you don't have rights to stop people from going into
your land to get to the fruit. So the same way you
can't make the fruit forbidden, it's not yours, how can you make
access into the yard forbidden? You don't own the rights to access
into the yard. So how can you make that forbidden? So the
Gemara says, so אמר עולא באומדים אילנות על הגבולין. Amar Ulla be-omdim
ilanot al ha-gvulin. Basically what we're talking about is that all the
trees are right there by the edge of the property. So what?
So he says an interesting thing. The Torah only gives the poor
people or whoever rights to enter my yard for the sake of
getting the fruit. Let's say they don't need to get into my
yard to get the fruit. All of the trees are right by
the border and they can just put up a ladder right by
the edge of my property and go up and pick the apples,
assuming that at least for the apples that are on that side
of the border, they don't need to go in. So if there
was a scenario, let's say it wasn't apples, let's say it was
wheat and I had just one row of wheat that was totally
accessible from the edge of my property. They don't have a right
to go into my property. Let them cut down the wheat standing
outside of my property. Okay, so that's actually quite a fascinating question
we never ask ourselves when the Torah says all the poor can
come and eat the fruit, which is how much can I have
I lost total rights of ownership to access to my yard or
is it no, they have limited rights for the purpose of getting
that fruit and actually I can tell them hey, you don't have
to enter my yard for this. Okay, which also raises questions like
would I be able to say that if it was more convenient
for them to enter my yard? Like it was theoretically possible but
it was more difficult? It's not clear. But that's what he says.
Yes, you actually do have rights to prevent them from entering your
yard if they can access it in another way. So that's what
he says. על הגבול. Al ha-gvul. רבי שמעון בן אליקים Rabbi Shimon
ben Elyakim אמר amar no, גזירה שמא ישהא בעמידה. Gezeirah shema yish'ha
ba-amidah. A similar point that they do not have unfettered access. They
have a right to come in, but they don't have a right
to stay there and tarry after they're done collecting the fruit. So
therefore if I say you cannot be in my yard, I do
have the right to make it forbidden for them to be in
my yard by a neder, not just by a property right, for
them to be in my yard longer than it takes them to
collect the fruit. And therefore that they would be forbidden, they would
transgress my neder if they waited around longer. Okay, so why doesn't
the mishnah just say they're not allowed to stay in my yard
any longer than it takes them to get the fruit? Why does
it say they can't go in my yard at all? Because then
rabbinically we won't let them go in the yard at all because
we would be afraid that they would come to stay to hang
out there after they collected the fruit and transgress the neder. Okay,
so this is like fascinating. I think when we think about שמיטה
shemitah it never starts to occur to us about what right do
I stay, but it makes a certain amount of sense. Like what,
like I can have people just camping out on my yard and
they can do and they can build tents and they can start
like living in my yard on שמיטה? shemitah? No. Presumably it's a
right of access for the sake of the fruit. So actually therefore
I can kick them out if they're abusing that right. But the
interesting thing here is that because they would I have I do
retain my property rights for them not to stay longer than necessary
and I can make that forbidden on them by neder, then we
won't let them access
it
at
all. I'll just say, I got a huge yard, I mean it's
crazy. Why doesn't everybody do this? All right, I've got this huge
yard and I, you know, this huge field and I'll basically say
all my property is forbidden, so now they cannot get into any
of, all they can get is the stuff that's right at the
border. I don't know, it's a really good question, like, you know,
how people didn't use this as a way to completely avoid the
consequences of שמיטה. shmita. I mean, and why the rabbis would have
made a גזירה gezera about this, right? I mean, it's very nice
to make a גזירה gezera of שמא, shema, but that גזירה gezera
has the effect of preventing people of, right, it's all rabbinic now
we're finding out because biblically I don't have that right, they have
the right to come in, I don't have the right to forbid
it, but because of our concern that they'll come to transgress rabbinically
we make them unable to access. What?
Wouldn't it violate the intention of שמיטה?
shmita? Yeah, I know, that's what I'm saying. I don't know. It's
a very, it's a really crazy idea, right? That's גזירה דרבנן gezera
de-rabbanan with such, I mean, somebody, if we could figure it out
in two minutes, then somebody who's got millions of dollars of fruit
or thousands of dollars of fruit, it would not take people too
long to figure out that this is a way to protect all
of your property on שמיטה. shmita. Yeah, I don't know how this
would, like, I don't know how the rabbis could have made such
גזירה. gezera. I don't know.
And you can pick it yourself, your own fruit too.
Right, meaning, for your own consumption. You cannot sort of harvest it
as a, like, as an owner would in terms of, you know,
to take it all. So
maybe that's the point, that there's very little to benefit from. But
I don't know, you could imagine that what you could do is
towards the end of שמיטה... shmita... well, I guess the question is
if there would be stuff that would remain good after שמיטה shmita
would be over, right? I mean, it would still have קדושת שמיטה
kedushat shmita on it, right? Yeah, I'd have to think about what
the consequences of that would be. All right, so the גמרא gemara
says like this, ובשביעית אין יורד לתוך שדהו, u-vi-shvi-it ein yored le-toch
sadehu, oh we just did that.
Okay, so that was that. Next משנה. mishna. Wow, we're just, we're
just zooming through here. המודר הנאה מחברו, ha-mudar hana-ah me-chaveiro, לא ישאילנו.
lo yash'ileinu. Now someone takes a vow not to get benefit from
his friend, he cannot...
now the question is who's the him here? But okay, ראובן Reuven
can't get benefit from שמעון. Shimon. So שמעון Shimon can't lend ראובן
Reuven objects, ולא ישאל ממנו, ve-lo yish'al mimenu, and cannot borrow objects
from him. לא ילוונו, lo yelvennu, can't lend him money, ולא ילווה
ממנו, ve-lo yilveh mimenu, or borrow money from him. לא ימכור לו,
lo yimkor lo, ולא יקח ממנו, ve-lo yikach mimenu, don't sell and
don't purchase from him. So we sort of understand that if שמעון,
Shimon, you know, if ראובן Reuven can't get benefit from שמעון, Shimon,
that he can't borrow money from שמעון, Shimon, you know, borrow objects
from שמעון, Shimon, etc. But why can't it be in the reverse?
Right? Why can't שמעון Shimon borrow objects from him? So that's what
the גמרא gemara is going to ask. Let's take a look at
the גמרא. gemara. We'll get a little ahead. בשלמא, bishlama, says גמרא,
gemara, לא ילוונו, lo yelvennu, דקמתהני ליה. de-kamithane lei. We understand, don't
lend him money. שמעון Shimon can't lend him money because then he's
benefiting him. אלא לא ילווה הימנו, ella lo yilveh himmenu, מאי קמהני
ליה? mai kamhani lei? But why can't שמעון Shimon borrow money from
him? What type of benefit is שמעון Shimon giving ראובן? Reuven? ובשלמא
לא ילווה הימנו ולא יקח הימנו, u-vishlama lo yilveh himmenu ve-lo yikach
himmenu, דקמתהני מיניה. de-kamithane minei.
So we also get that it's a little bit funny, the sort
of switching, some people have a slightly different גירסא. girsa. But anyway,
we get also the problem about not, you know, borrowing, not, you
know... one minute. ובשלמא לא ילווה הימנו ולא יקח הימנו דקמתהני מיניה,
אלא לא ישאל הימנו מאי קמתהני מיניה? u-vishlama lo yilveh himmenu ve-lo
yikach himmenu de-kamithane minei, ella lo yish'al himmenu mai kamithane minei? We
get don't borrow from him and don't take from him because you're
getting benefit from him, but why not borrow from him? What are
you getting benefit from? Which is, which means going back like on
ראובן. Reuven. We understand why ראובן Reuven can't, no, wait a minute.
Yeah, that's a weird גירסא. girsa.
If you take a look at the ר"ן, Ran, the ר"ן'ס Ran's
גירסא girsa is different. The ר"ן'ס Ran's גירסא girsa is top here,
בשלמא לא ילווה ממנו ולא יקח ממנו ולא ישאל ממנו, bishlama lo
yilveh mimenu ve-lo yikach mimenu ve-lo yish'al mimenu, right? I get why
you can't borrow and purchase and, like, borrow money, purchase and borrow
objects. Okay, but why, says אלא לא ישאילנו ולא ילוונו ולא ימכור
לו מאי? ella lo yash'ileinu ve-lo yelvennu ve-lo yimkor lo mai? But
why can't you lend him objects, lend him, you know, lend him
money, or sell him objects? Okay, so which is a better read.
Our גירסא girsa is a little bit funny here. But anyway, the
point is why, you know, what's the purpose of the second half
of all the cases in the משנה? mishna? We understand why you
can't get things... the ראובן Reuven can't get things from שמעון, Shimon,
but why can he not give things, you know, as it were
for שמעון? Shimon? So אמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא, amar Rabbi Yose
bar Chanina, כגון שנדרו הנאה זה מזה. kegon shenadaru hana-ah ze mize.
The case in the משנה mishna is ראובן Reuven can't get from
שמעון Shimon and שמעון Shimon can't get from ראובן, Reuven, which is
not so interesting because then it's just saying the same thing in
two directions. Don't borrow money whether you're ראובן Reuven or whether you're
שמעון, Shimon, don't borrow money. Like it's not really saying that it
was... you know, it's not really interesting in that way. אביי אמר,
Abaye amar, גזירה לשאול משום להשאיל וכן בכולהו. gezera lish'ol mishum lehash'il
vechein bekulhu. אביי Abaye says it's a גזירה gezera not to borrow
because you might come to lend, and so too for all of
them. No, אביי Abaye says no, the point of the משנה Mishna
is we don't let, even though in principle what you really can't
do is שמעון Shimon can't, is ראובן Reuven can't borrow money from
שמעון, Shimon, we don't let him lend money to שמעון Shimon in
order that he shouldn't come that he shouldn't borrow. And although he
can't go ahead and borrow objects, we don't let him lend objects
because he'll because it's the flip side and he'll come to actually
borrow objects. It creates too much of reciprocity and so on. Okay,
so אביי Abaye says the גזירה, gezeirah, which is probably more the
פשט pshat of the משנה. Mishna. Now I want to just say
two things, which is number one is the question about sale, who's
the beneficiary of a transaction, right? So based on your sort of
גרסא girsa here in the גמרא, Gemara, like the גמרא Gemara is
saying, well, we get why you can't buy, but why can you
not sell? It gets to the question we raised before. Do we
assume a standard sale both the buyer and the seller benefit? Do
we assume that fundamentally it's the buyer that benefits, right, which sort
of would work, so we get why you can't borrow money and
buy objects, but why can't you lend money or give or sell
objects? The presumption that the גמרא Gemara often has, which is that,
you know, is that it's the sort of borrow it's the purchaser
that benefits, but based on your גרסא girsa of the גמרא, Gemara,
right, is whether, you know, the buying and the selling, at least
that would have been the one that would have been the one
that would have made sense in two directions. And that might explain
also אביי's Abaye גזירה, gezeirah, right, you might want to say that
look, buying and selling is a case where both the buyer and
the seller benefit. So that one you can't go in either direction.
And once that one you can't go in either direction, we won't
allow the borrowing to go in either direction either, right, but at
least one of those might be one where both sides benefit. The
other point that I'll make is is that this actually for people
who have learned the first משנה mishna in עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara,
right, the first משנה mishna of עבודה זרה Avoda Zara is, right,
three like things you can't do with pagans, you know, three days
before their holidays. So, and one of them basically and basically it's
this list of things. You can't sell from them and buy from
them, lend them money, borrow from them money, lend give them objects,
borrow from them objects, and the whole type of a thing, which
is a similar idea of like keeping a type of a distance.
And the גמרא Gemara there also asks, well, we understand one direction,
maybe you don't want to give them benefit right before their holiday,
but why do you want not want to get benefit from them?
And אביי Abaye basically says the same answer. אביי Abaye says it's
like גזירה. gezeirah. Okay, which is, you know, maybe it is fundamentally
one direction, but we don't want to we want to forbid the
other direction. But the reason it's interesting is because, you know, here
we see that this is like it also reminds you of the
whole idea of חרם, cherem, like if somebody's in חרם cherem you
don't want to do certain, you know, interactions with that person, keep
the distance, right? So on the one hand, very interesting as we
just got through like a whole פרק perek that ראובן Reuven can't
get הנאה hana'ah from שמעון, Shimon, but there's all these types of
things you can do, pay a ביקור חולים bikur cholim call and
heal him and pay off his debts and like there's a million
things you can do even though you can't get benefit, right, but
at least this collection of direct transactions lending and borrowing and selling
things and so on, like this is אסור assur in both directions.
And this and that really at least creates at least a certain
wall, like prevent certain types of, you know, of interaction between them,
and it's the same type of division that is created between Jews
and non-Jews around non-Jewish holidays. So my point is that it's not
maybe just a technical question of איסור הנאה, issur hana'ah, right? I
mean if we're making גזירות, gezeiras, for God's sake, there are so
many things we just got through allowing in the previous משניות, mishnayot,
right? I mean I can pay off your creditors, I can pay
your wife, I can do that, I can do a million things,
you know, but maybe it's like this is a collection of sort
of showing the sort of, you know, the the the difference that
the, you know, that the wall between these two people, and it's
reflected in also the types of stuff that we find in עבודה
זרה Avoda Zara which is coming from a very different type of
a concern. Okay.